{"tossups": [{"question": "Alberto Cantino was sent to this empire under the guise of negotiating a horse trade to steal maps of this empire\u2019s overseas discoveries. A desire to settle the \u201cMoluccas issue\u201d prompted this country to sign a 1529 treaty in a neighboring empire. Abu Abdallah Mohammad II\u2019s deposition as Sultan of Morocco prompted this empire to intervene in the Battle of Alcacer Quibir, which brought an end to its Aviz Dynasty. For ten points, name this empire that, in 1580, joined Spain in the Iberian Union.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b> (or the<b> Portuguese</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man proclaimed that he would appoint Max Roach as Secretary of Defense and Charles Mingus as Secretary of Peace in a satirical 1964 presidential run meant to raise money for SCLC and CORE. This musician avoided the traditional walking bass line in a composition recorded by Sarah Vaughan under the title \u201cInterlude.\u201d During his time in Earl Hines\u2019 band, this composer of \u201cSalt Peanuts\u201d started to develop bebop along with saxophonist Charlie Parker. \u201cA Night In Tunisia\u201d was written by, for ten points, what jazz musician who played a \u201cbent\u201d trumpet?", "answer": "John Birks \u201cDizzy\u201d<b> Gillespie</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s grandson was murdered 16 years after he set fire to an apartment, killing his grandmother, this man\u2019s widow. This man disputed that his father died in a streetcar accident, instead believing he was killed by the Black Legion, who had burned down their house. In 1995, this man\u2019s daughter Qubilah admitted to a plot to kill Louis Farrakhan, who she held responsible for this man\u2019s death. This man claimed his ancestors had been imposed on by a \u201cblue-eyed devil\u201d when explaining changing his surname to reflect his lost African heritage. For ten points, name this man who was assassinated in 1965 after leaving the Nation of Islam.", "answer": "<b> Malcolm X</b> (accept Malcolm<b> Little</b>; accept el-Hajj Malik el-<b>Shabazz</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A section of a speech that discusses this symbol claims that the doors to America should be \u201copen to anyone with the will and the heart to get here.\u201d A John F. Kennedy speech about this symbol declared\u201cFor of those to whom much is given, much is required.\u201d This symbol was used extensively in campaigning by Ronald Reagan, who adapted his description from a speech delivered from the<em> Arbella</em> by John Winthrop in 1630. For ten points, name this symbolism that likens America to the \u201clight of the world,\u201dtaken from the Sermon on the Mount.", "answer": "A<b> City</b> up<b>on</b> a<b> Hill</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Approximate solutions to this problem can be found using Christofides algorithm, and the Held-Karp algorithm solves this problem in \u201c<em>n</em> squared times two to the<em> n</em>\u201d time. Richard Karp\u2019s 1972 work on the cycle problem implied that this problem is NP-complete. Merrill Flood was motivated to study this optimization problem while trying to determine optimal school bus routes. For ten points, name this famous problem in computer science that, metaphorically, seeks to find the shortest route that visits each city on a certain type of worker\u2019s agenda.", "answer": "<b> traveling salesman</b> problem", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "In this event, a crash-landed Zero was captured intact, the first time the Allies had done so. Father John McGrath observed incoming enemy forces from his post on Bathurst Island, but because they were mistakenly thought to be allied, the air raid sirens were not sounded until this event had begun. Chuichi Nagumo led this attack to prevent allied opposition to the Japanese invasions of Timor and Java. Over 200 aircraft took part in, for ten points, what February 1942 attack by Japanese forces on a northern Australian city?", "answer": "bombing of<b> Darwin</b> (or Battle of<b> Darwin</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Under this ruler, Juan Pistarini served as Minister of Public Works and built a massive international airport. After this man mysteriously lost his secretary general Jose Rucci to assassins, he ordered Jose Rega to fund the Triple A death squad to counteract left-wing extremists. In 1973, this man planned a massacre of leftist Montoneros who had come to an airport to welcome this man from exile. This man, who was supported by the<em> descamisados</em>, or the shirtless ones, died in 1974 and was succeeded by his third wife, Isabel. For ten points, name this president of Argentina.", "answer": "Juan<b> Per\u00b4on</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Governor Warren McCray vetoed a bill that would have let this group sponsor a day at the State Fair. A war veteran from Evansville led a splinter faction of this group and revealed the “Little Black Boxes,” lists of politicians under its influence, after he was imprisoned for kidnapping and torturing teacher Madge Oberholtzer in 1925. D.C.D.C. Stephenson led a massively popular branch of, for ten points, what organization, for which he published the newspaper<em> The Fiery Cross</em>?", "answer": "<b> Ku Klux Klan</b> (or<b> KKK</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One artist created multi-sectioned works in this medium to illustrate her picture books about Cassie Louise Lightfoot. \u201cTar Beach\u201d and \u201cWho\u2019s Afraid of Aunt Jemima\u201d are examples of \u201cstory\u201d types of this art medium created by artist Faith Ringgold. Cleve Jones began an ongoing project of this type that lists names like Rock Hudson and Freddie Mercury, known as the \u201cAIDS Memorial.\u201d Signals were sent on the Underground Railroad by displaying, for ten points, what artworks, made by piecing together layers of batting and small sections of fabric, that also serve as warm blankets?", "answer": "<b> quilt</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "After an anti-Catholic poster was attached to this man\u2019s bedchamber in the Affair of the Placards, he reversed his previous toleration of Protestants. He was forced to give up Burgundy in the Treaty of Madrid. This man pursued an \u201cunholy alliance\u201d with Suleiman the Magnificent for support against his greatest rival, a Habsburg monarch to whom he lost the 1525 battle of Pavia during the Italian Wars. For ten points, name this Valois king of France, who fought against Charles V.", "answer": "<b> Francis I</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a Supreme Court case originating from this state, the court mandated an \u201cessential nexus\u201d between legitimate state interests and permit conditions for regulatory takings. Warrantless searches of cell phones were ruled unconstitutional after David Riley sued this state. A \u201cthree-prong standard\u201d was established to determine whether works have \u201cserious artistic value\u201d or are obscene in the case<em> Miller v.</em> this state. For ten points, name this state where the CRASH police unit\u2019s excessive force was the subject of<em> US v.</em> <em>Los Angeles Police Protection League</em>.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The book<em> Lines Drawn Upon the Water</em> discusses how the indigenous people of this country struggled with the psychology of imposed European-style borders. The native people of this country had their land transferred in the Numbered Treaties. In 1966, 12-year-old Chanie Wenjack ran away from a residential school for natives in this country and died of exposure. This country\u2019s Constitution Act of 1982 defines\u201caboriginal people\u201d as a group including the mixed-race descendants of natives and European settlers, as well as the Inuit. For ten points, name this country where the First Nations have negotiated with Prime Ministers like Paul Martin and Stephen Harper.", "answer": "<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "M.C. Kelly co-authored a piece that claimed that the rise of noctilucent clouds after this event explains that it was caused by something icy. Some scholars use this event to explain the lack of a rim around Lake Cheko. The TRINITY institute examined a landform created after this event and found modern permafrost on the outer layers but older, non-Earthly matter below. The Suslov crater was created in this event, which flattened nearly 800 square miles of the East Siberian taiga. A comet probably caused, for ten points, what 1908 explosion in Russia?", "answer": "<b> Tunguska</b> event (accept additional information as long as<b> Tunguska</b> is said; prompt on descriptive answers related to a meteor/comet/etc. blowing up trees in Siberia that don\u2019t include Tunguska)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {}, {"question": "It is believed that this city\u2019s 1899 outbreak of plague was caused by the offloading of the<em> America</em> <em>Maru</em>; that came a year before this city faced a wave of fires that were blamed on Chinese immigrants. This city became the capital of a kingdom after a warrior won the Battle of Leaping Mullet. The name of this city\u2019s Hale Ali\u2019i was changed to \u2018Iolani Palace in the 1860s. For ten points, name this city, home to Waikiki Beach and Diamond Head, that became a US state capital in 1959.", "answer": "<b> Honolulu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man claimed that Americans were \u201caverse to dictatorship\u201d while conducting a 1934 interview, explaining to Adolf Hitler why his press coverage in the U.S. was so negative. This man founded the Municipal Ownership League to oppose Tammany Hall in a failed campaign for the (+) mayorship of New York City in 1907. Two decades earlier, this man\u2019s father gave him control of the</b><em><b> San Francisco Examiner</b></em><b>, launching a career that led to ownership of the (*) </b> <em>New York Journal</em> and the use of sensationalist \u201cyellow\u201d journalism practices. For ten points, name this American newspaper magnate and rival of Joseph Pulitzer.", "answer": "William Randolph<b> Hearst</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>\u201cThe Shining City\u201d was a palace built for a leader of this state. Muhammad al-Mahdi ordered the assassination of a leader of this state after that leader decided to attack Alfonso</b> <b>V. This state\u2019s technological advances included the importation of (+)</b> <b>toothpaste and</b> <b>deodorant from Baghdad. This state was briefly ruled by the Hammudid Dynasty, and after the assassination Abd al-Rahman Sanchuelo, it saw the Fitna of (*) </b> al-Andalus. After 1031, this state split into many taifa, including one at Zaragoza. Hisham II led this state, and his chamberlain Almanzor later took power. For ten points, name this caliphate that was ruled by the Umayyad Dynasty in Iberia.", "answer": "Caliphate of<b> C\u00b4ordoba</b> (prompt on Umayyad before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>William James delivered a lecture series focusing on the reciprocal relationship between the central figures of this theory \u201cAnd Their Environment.\u201d Herbert Spencer criticized</b> <b>this theory by claiming that \u201cthe genesis of [its (+)</b> <b>central figure] depends on the long</b> <b>series of complex influences.\u201d The originator of this theory, Thomas Carlyle, claimed that\u201cThe history of the world is but the (*)</b> biography of\u201d its central figures. For ten points, name this historical theory that claims that great heroes and personalities had the greatest impact on history.", "answer": "<b> Great Man</b> theory", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}